Guide to the Thomas Carlyle Collection GEN MSS 677
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Thomas Carlyle collection
1750-1951
1827-1882
GEN MSS 677
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
7.17
(24 boxes) + 1 broadside
The Thomas Carlyle Collection is a mixed-provenance collection of material by and about Thomas Carlyle. Material includes writings, notes, maps, and correspondence that document Carlyle's research on German history and literature and on Oliver Cromwell, among other topics.
Carlyle, Thomas, 1795-1881
Neuberg, Joseph, 1806-1867
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired by gift and purchase from various sources, as noted on individual folders or on the catalog cards in Folder 1. A large portion of the papers was purchased at Sotheby's (lot 199) on the A.H. Childs Fund, 1932.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of the collection are available on microfilm.
Arrangement
Arrangement of the Thomas Carlyle Collection reflects the existing organization in 2009.
Thomas Carlyle, 1795-1881
Thomas Carlyle, biographer, literary critic, and historian, was born December 4, 1795 in Ecclefechan, Scotland and died February 5, 1881. Among his writings are the literary biography The Life of Friedrich Schiller (1825), the novel Sartor Resartus (1833-1834), the series of lectures On Heroes, Hero-Worship & the Heroic in History (1840), and History of Friedrich II of Prussia, called Frederick the Great (1858-1865).
Scope and Contents
The Thomas Carlyle Collection is a mixed-provenance collection of material by and about Thomas Carlyle. Material includes writings, notes, maps, and correspondence that document Carlyle's research on German history and literature and on Oliver Cromwell, among other topics. The bulk of the papers relate to Carlyle's History of Friedrich II of Prussia, called Frederick the Great and include maps, research notes, correspondence, drafts, and corrected proofs. Notes by Carlyle's assistant Joseph Neuberg (d. 1867) reveal the extent and character of Neuberg's contributions to the work. There is also a substantial amount of material related to Oliver Cromwell's Letters and Speeches, including an annotated three-volume set of the printed work that was used to prepare a revised edition, and several folders of contributions by various correspondents. Other papers include drafts of essays and a book-length work on the history of German literature, letters to and from Carlyle about diverse aspects of his life and work, and photographs of Carlyle and his wife Jane Welsh Carlyle. Of particular interest are holograph drafts of Past and Present and fragments of Chartism.
Authors, Scottish -- 19th century -- Archives; British literature -- 19th century; Scottish literature -- 19th century; Prussia (Germany) -- History -- 18th century; German literature; Photographs; Maps (documents); Sculpture (visual work) -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Carlyle, Thomas, 1795-1881; Carlyle, Jane Welsh, 1801-1866; Cromwell, Oliver; Frederick, King of Prussia, II, 1712-1786; Neuberg, Joseph, 1806-1867; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892
- Catalog cards, 2 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Catalog cards were created by Yale Library staff at or around the time of accession and contain descriptions and provenance information for material in the collection. Much of the information on the cards is duplicated on individual folders.
- Sotzmann, Daniel Friedrich, Map of Poland and adjoining provinces, 1793; 2; (4 sheets, 59 x 48 cm)
- Mazburg, Georg Ignaz von, Post Charte der Kais. Konig. Erblande, 1783; (1 sheet, 54 x 80 cm)
- Polen, Litauen und Kurland im Jahr 1775 [1793, 1796], 1820?; (3 sheets, 44 x 50 cm)
- Buna, Wilhelm C., [Map of Bavaria], 1760?; 3; (9 sheets, 56 x 54 cm)
- Carta geometrica del granducato di Toscana, undated; (1 sheet, 41.4 x 38 cm) (Box Bsd)
- [Map of Casentino?], undated; (1 sheet, 31.5 x 27 cm) (Box Bsd)
- Munch, P.A. Karte over Norge till Brug ved elementaerundervüsningen udarbeidet af P.A. Munch., 1857; (1 sheet, 54 x 42.5 cm) (Box Bsd)
- Reymann, Daniel Gottlob, Charte vom Westphaelschen Kreise., 1804; (1 sheet, 54.5 x 46 cm) (Box Bsd)
- Society for the diffusion of useful knowledge, London. The environs of Paris., 1832; (1 sheet, 29.5 x 38 cm) (Box Bsd)
- Tardieu, Pierre, Carte de France., 1833; (1 sheet, 52 x 73.5 cm) (Box Bsd)
- Material used in writing the History of Friedrich II of Prussia, called Frederick the Great, including notes, and transcripts of documents in the hand of Joseph Neuberg, 1850s-1860s, undated; 11 (Box 2)
- Material used in writing the History of Friedrich II of Prussia, called Frederick the Great, including notes, and transcripts of documents in the hand of Joseph Neuberg, 1850s-1860s, undated; 5 (Box 3)
- Richard Brooks, notes on Yale University's acquisition of material related to Thomas Carlyle's History of Friedrich II of Prussia, typescript (copy), with clippings, 1932, undated (Box 3)
- Material removed for a Yale University exhibit on Carlyle in 1956, 1750s-1850s (Box 3)
- Correspondence, 1859-1867, undated; 2 (Box 3)
- Material used in writing the History of Friedrich II of Prussia, called Frederick the Great, including notes, correspondence, and fragments of proofs, 1850s, undated; 10 (Box 4)
- Material used in writing the History of Friedrich II of Prussia, called Frederick the Great, including notes, correspondence, and fragments of proofs, 1850s-1860s, undated; 6 (Box 5)
- Preliminary sketches of chapters of History of Friedrich II of Prussia, called Frederick the Great, holograph and manuscripts by Joseph Neuberg, undated; 14 (Box 6)
- "A course of lectures on the history of literature by Mr. Carlyle, 1838," manuscript (Box 6)
- History of Friedrich II of Prussia, called Frederick the Great, drafts, holograph, undated; 11 (Box 7)
- History of Friedrich II of Prussia, called Frederick the Great, proofs, undated; 2 (Box 8)
- History of Friedrich II of Prussia, called Frederick the Great, proofs, undated; 2 (Box 9)
- Carlyle, Thomas, Oliver Cromwell's Letters and Speeches, London: Chapman and Hall, Volume 1, 1850 (Box 10)
- Carlyle, Thomas, Oliver Cromwell's Letters and Speeches, London: Chapman and Hall, Volume 2, 1850 (Box 11)
- Carlyle, Thomas, Oliver Cromwell's Letters and Speeches, London: Chapman and Hall, Volume 3, 1850 (Box 12)
- The Rakes of Mallow, manuscript fragment in the hand of Joseph Neuberg annotated by Carlyle, undated (Box 13)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Microfilm available.
- Portraits (photographs and reproduction of a painting) of Jane Welsh Carlyle and Thomas Carlyle., 1865, undated (Box 13)
- Carlyle Memorial Fund correspondence, 1881-1882 (Box 13)
- Signatures of Jane Welsh Carlyle, clipped from letters, undated (Box 13)
- Letter: Jane Welsh Carlyle to Mr. Cross, undated (Box 13)
- Letter: Jane Welsh Carlyle to Mrs. Cunningham, undated (Box 13)
- Letter: Jane Welsh Carlyle to Mrs. [Alexander] Gilchrist, undated (Box 13)
- Letter: Jane Welsh Carlyle to Mrs. Mackenzie, undated (Box 13)
- Letter: Jane Welsh Carlyle to [John] Ruskin, undated (Box 13)
- Letter: Jane Welsh Carlyle to Helen Welsh, undated (Box 13)
- Letter: Jane Welsh Carlyle to Mr. Woolner, undated (Box 13)
- Letter: Margaret Aitken Carlyle to her daughter, undated (Box 13)
- Letter: Mary Aitken Carlyle to John Ruskin, 1873 November 12 (Box 13)
- Carlyle, Thomas, article on Goethe's Faust, holograph, 1832 or 1833 (Box 13)
- Carlyle, Thomas, "1840. Members of the Long Parliament," holograph (Box 13)
- Carlyle, Thomas, "The English Talent for Governing", circa 1848 (Box 13)
- Carlyle, Thomas, biographical material for an essay on Grosshopf Müllner, holograph, 1831 (Box 13)
- Carlyle, Thomas, notes on the Carlyle pedigree, holograph, 1865 (Box 13)
- Carlyle, Thomas, Rejected fragments of Chartism, holograph, undated (Box 13)
- Carlyle, Thomas, "Industrial regiments," holograph, 1848 (Box 13)
- Carlyle, Thomas, "Creeds," holograph, 1852 (Box 13)
- Carlyle, Thomas, "Latter Day Pamphlets," holograph, 1848 (Box 13)
- Carlyle, Thomas, "Marlboro," holograph and Joseph Neuberg's hand, undated (Box 13)
- Carlyle, Thomas, notes on Norse literature, holograph, 1840 (Box 13)
- Carlyle, Thomas, manuscript on the project of appointing the civil service by merit alone, holograph, 1854 (Box 13)
- Carlyle, Thomas, poems, including translations from German, holograph, 1820s-1840s (Box 13)
- Photograph of Thomas Carlyle, signed, undated (Box 13)
- Carlyle, Thomas, manuscript on the Reform Measure, holograph, 1867 (Box 13)
- Carlyle, Thomas, "Thirty-five unpublished letters of Oliver Cromwell" (fragment), holograph, 1847 (Box 13)
- Photographs of Thomas Carlyle, one signed, undated (Box 13)
- "History of the Thirty Years War, Book I," manuscript possibly in the hand of John Carlyle, undated (Box 13)
- Carlyle, Thomas, "History of German Literature," holograph, circa 1829 (Box 13)
- Shine, Hill (editor), Carlyle's Unfinished History of German Literature, Lexington: University of Kentucky Press, 1951 (Box 13)
- Carlyle, Thomas, "Simon Brodie had a cow..." (verse), holograph, 1859 December 19 (Box 14)
- Carlyle, Thomas, quotations, holograph, 1851, undated (Box 14)
- Carlyle, Thomas, "Journey to Germany, Autumn 1858," holograph and typescript, 1858, undated; 2 (Box 14)
- Letters: Thomas Carlyle to Mr. Cunningham and to unidentified recipients, 1852, 1865 (Box 14)
- Letters: Thomas Carlyle to unidentified recipients, 1834-1847, undated; 5 (Box 14)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to Lady Rosina Bulwer Lytton, 1850 December 31 (Box 14)
- Letters: Thomas Carlyle to unidentified recipients, 1856-1872; 7 (Box 14)
- Letters: Thomas Carlyle to Rev. David Aitken, 1835; 2 (Box 14)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to Sarah Taylor Austin, 1850 February 17 (Box 14)
- Letters: Thomas Carlyle to James Ballantine, 1844-1858; 2 (Box 14)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to Henry Barnard, 1835 June 12 (Box 14)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to John Aitken Carlyle, 1849 August 2 (Box 14)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to E. Chapman, 1859 November 11 (Box 14)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to John Chapman, 1854 July 18 (Box 14)
- Letters: Thomas Carlyle to Chapman and Hall (publishers), 1846, 1867; 2 (Box 14)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to William Dougal Christie, 1863 June 2 (Box 14)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to Henry Cole, 1840 April 25 (Box 14)
- Letters: Thomas Carlyle to Thomas Constable, 1850, 1855 (Box 14)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to George Lillie Craik, 1847 April 12 (Box 14)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to Edward FitzGerald, 1846 September (Box 14)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to the editor of The Dumfries and Galloway Courier, 1830 April 12 (Box 14)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to James A. Froude, 1860 October 23 (Box 14)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to Alexander Gilchrist, 1856 September 2 (Box 14)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to Grant, 1859 March 17 (Box 14)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to John Grieg, 1846 June 20 (Box 14)
- Letters: Thomas Carlyle to Leigh Hunt, 1836, undated; 2 (Box 14)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to Margaret Hunt, 1866 November 9 (Box 14)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to Frederic Madden, 1856 November 12 (Box 14)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to [Fr. Mimm?], 1844 June 6 (Box 14)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to Mrs. Montague, 1825 July 18 (Box 14)
- Letters: Thomas Carlyle to Katherine Aurora Kirkpatrick, 1868-1871 (Box 14)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to "Mr. Putnam's manager", 1846 July 10 (Box 14)
- Letters: Thomas Carlyle to John James Ruskin, 1860-1866; 3 (Box 14)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to Miss Scott, 1850 March 16 (Box 14)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to William Bell Scott, 1851 June 17 (Box 14)
- Letters: Thomas Carlyle to James Hutchison Stirling, 1854-1868 (Box 14)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to Robert Tait, 1867 November 30 (Box 14)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to Eliot Warburton, 1851 November 23 (Box 14)
- Letters: Thomas Carlyle to William White, 1867 (Box 14)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to Mr. Williams, 1853 October (Box 14)
- Note: Thomas Carlyle to Messrs. Williams and Norgate, 1855 June 27 (Box 14)
- Letters: Sir Joseph Edgar Boehm to Thomas Carlyle, 1874 (Box 14)
- Letter: Thomas Markby to Thomas Carlyle, 1865 May 4 (Box 14)
- Notebook for Oliver Cromwell's Letters and Speeches, holograph, undated (Box 15)
- Notes for the articles "The Diamond Necklace" and "Cagliostro," holograph, 1830s (Box 15)
- Letters: Thomas Carlyle to Richard Hengist Horne, 1838-1839 (Box 15)
- Letters: Thomas Carlyle to unidentified, 1842-1843; 2 (Box 15)
- Album apparently kept by Helen M. Welsh, inscribed by Thomas Carlyle, 1830-1839 (Box 15)
- Letters: Thomas Carlyle to Christian Bunsen, 1843 (Box 15)
- Letters: Thomas Carlyle to unidentified recipients, 1844-1849; 3 (Box 15)
- Carlyle, Thomas, Past and Present, holograph, circa 1843 (Box 15)
- Carlyle, Thomas, "Sir Robert Peel," holograph, circa 1849 (Box 15)
- Syllabus and ticket for "On Heroes, Hero-Worship, and the Heroic in Human History" (lecture series), printed version, 1840 (Box 15)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to unidentified recipient, 1850 March 16 (Box 15)
- Letters: Thomas Carlyle to William Edward Forster and to unidentified recipients, 1840-1847 (Box 15)
- Carlyle, Thomas, manuscript relating to Oliver Cromwell's Letters and Speeches ," holograph, undated (Box 15)
- Carlyle, Thomas, reading list on German literature, for the use of John Carlyle, 1827 September 11 (Box 15)
- Carlyle, Thomas, notes and memoranda related to Oliver Cromwell's Letters and Speeches, holograph, undated (Box 15)
- Carlyle, Thomas, Past and Present, holograph, circa 1843 (Box 15)
- Carlyle, Thomas, notes and memoranda relating to Oliver Cromwell's Letters and Speeches, holograph, 4 (Box 16)
- Various correspondents, contributions to Oliver Cromwell's Letters and Speeches, manuscript, 8 (Box 16)
- Various correspondents, contributions to Oliver Cromwell's Letters and Speeches, manuscript, 5 (Box 17)
- Oliver Cromwell's Letters and Speeches, draft, holograph, undated, 1880s
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to Connop Thirlwall, 1843 July 9 (Box 18)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to "Dear Taylor", 1849 March 26 (Box 18)
- Carlyle, Thomas. Quotation from his French Revolution, undated (Box 18)
- Carlyle, Thomas. Translation of Goethe's "Mason's Song," holograph, accompanied by letter from A. Carlyle to W.K. Dickson, 1929, undated (Box 18)
- Carlyle, Thomas. Calling card addressed to Henry Inglis, 1835 (Box 18)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to Barry W. Procter, undated (Box 18)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to "Dear Geraldine", 1864 December 8 (Box 18)
- Carlyle, Thomas. Autographed note, signed, with small autographed photograph, 1850 January 1 (Box 18)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to Edward Chapman, 1854 January 4 (Box 18)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to Eckermann, 1834 May 6 (Box 18)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to Mrs. Martin, 1874 May 6 (Box 18)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to [H.I. Merton?], 1844 March 29 (Box 18)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to Mrs. Barry W. Procter, undated (Box 18)
- Letters: Thomas Carlyle to his mother, 1840-1846 (Box 18)
- Letters: Thomas Carlyle to his sister, Jannet Carlyle Hanning, 1842-1871 (Box 18)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to Lord Monteagle, 1844 March 28 (Box 18)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to [Mary] Rich, 1838 April 19 (Box 18)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to "My dear Madam", 1837 March 27 (Box 18)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to unidentified recipient, accompanied by carte de visite, 1855 June 26 (Box 18)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to [George Henry] Lewes, accompanied by an engraving of Thomas Carlyle, 1852 March 2 (Box 18)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to Rev. W.J. Loewenberg, 1872 July 2 (Box 18)
- Letter: Thomas Carlyle to "My dear Sir", 1848 October 28 (Box 18)
- A stone from the rocks at Kollin, 1850 (Box 19)
- Bronze cast of Thomas Carlyle's hands by T. Woolner, 1800s (Box 22)
- Plaster cast of Thomas Carlyle's hands by T. Woolner, 1800s (Box 23)
- Key to private, sound-proof room in Cheyne Walk, Chelsea, 1800s (Box 24)
- Oversize Papers
  - Sotzmann, Daniel Friedrich, Map of Poland and adjoining provinces, 1793 (Box 20 (Oversize))
  - Mazburg, Georg Ignaz von, Post Charte der Kais. Konig. Erblande, 1783 (Box 20 (Oversize))
  - Polen, Litauen und Kurland im Jahr 1775 [1793, 1796], 1820 (Box 20 (Oversize))
  - Buna, Wilhelm C., [Map of Bavaria], 1760 (Box 20 (Oversize))
  - History of Friedrich II of Prussia, called Frederick the Great, draft, holograph, undated, 1850s (Box 21 (Oversize))
  - Oliver Cromwell's Letters and Speeches, draft, holograph, undated, 1880s (Box 21 (Oversize))